Guide to the Renée Jacobs photographs, 1979-2015 RL.11117
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Renée Jacobs photographs
1979-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jacobs, Renée
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.11117
15 Linear Feet 16 boxes; 1 oversize folder
Renée Jacobs is a documentary photographer and photojournalist whose project, "Slow Burn," documents the abandonment of Centralia, Pennsylvania due to an underground coal mine fire in the mid-1980s. Her archive includes negatives, contact sheets, gelatin silver work prints and exhibit prints, digital inkjet prints, and publication materials deriving from the project. There are also oral history interviews on audiocassette with residents of Centralia, as well as some correspondence, a 1979 federal government report on Centralia, and color photographs and negatives taken by another photographer who visited the town in 1987. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Biographical / Historical
Renée Jacobs' early photojournalism included assignments for The New York Times, Philadelphia Inquirer and many other newspapers and magazines. She received the Robert F. Kennedy Award for Outstanding Coverage of the Disadvanatged and her work is in the permanent collection of the John F. Kennedy Presidential Library. Slow Burn was originally published in 1986 and re-issued in 2010 to favorable reviews in The New York Times Review of Books and photo-eye. Renée Jacobs went on to study environmental law as a result of her work in Centralia. She practiced civil rights and constitutional law for fifteen years. In 2007 she returned to photography. Her work has been exhibited and published around the world, and has recieved the prestigious International Photography Award for Fine Art Nude among other honors.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, but original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Please contact Research Services in advance of your visit to request the production of listening copies.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Renee Jacobs Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2016.
Collection Overview
This collection contains Renée Jacobs' archive of her project Slow Burn: A Photodocument of Centralia, Pennslyvania. Slow Burn, first published in 1986 by University of Pennsylvania Press, chronicles Centralia’s demise from an underground coal mine fire and depicts a singular epic event in Pennsylvania history, representing the confluence of environmental, scientific, bureaucratic, and emotional tragedies. As an award winning photojournalist, Jacobs moved into a house in Centralia’s impact zone in 1983 to document, in photographs and interviews, the end stages of the tiny anthracite coal town’s unsuccessful fight to resolve the intractable problems that began with the mine fire in 1962 and culminated in the razing of the town by the federal government.
Photographer Shelby Lee Adams has written of the project stating:
"Where once there was familiarity with open doors and trusting hearts, in a community that could be your home anywhere in America, an invisible cancer grew. It’s the unseen, slow-moving nature of this underground burning that took Centralia apart. The human spirit doesn’t want to believe, see, or hear what can destroy our sanctified special places in the world. Renée Jacobs faithfully and compassionately documents in pictures and words the confusion, uncertainty, and fighting spirit of Centralia’s residents—and the painful destruction and relocation of the residents of this little Pennsylvania town. Slow Burn is a compelling story about—and for—all of us.”
The archive consist of more than 200 rolls of 35mm black and white film, the accompanying contact sheets, more than 1,000 silver gelatin work prints, contemporaneous news articles, oral history interviews and vintage exhibition prints. Additionally, the archives include maquettes for the original 1986 book and the 2010 re-issue, as well as prints with printer’s notations.
Separated Materials
Three copies of Slow Burn (1986; 2010 hardback; 2010 paperback) have been removed from the archive for individual cataloging as print items.
Centralia (Pa.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works; Centralia (Pa.) -- History -- Pictorial works; Documentary photographers; Documentary Photography -- Pennsylvania; Audiocassettes; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Contact sheets; Digital prints; Gelatin silver prints; Mock-ups; Oral histories (document genre); Roll negatives; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Jacobs, Renée
- Slow Burn, 1979-2015
  - Bureau of Mines and Office of Surface Mining government report re: Centralia, 1979 (Box 15)
  - Original Negative Binders 1 and 2, 1983-1985; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Negatives (miscellaneous), 1986 and undated; 2 folders (Box 15)
    Scope and Contents
    Loose negatives, some with contact strips included. One set includes a caption re: Centralia Demolition.
  - Contact sheets, 1986; 6 folders 208 contact sheets (Box 2)
    Missing pages 40, 62, 101, 117-118, 135
  - CD of contact sheet scans (Box 2, Data-cd RL-11117-OP-0001)
  - Slides (Black & White, Color), 1986; 5 folders 35mm slides, including slide presentation of book (Box 3)
  - Slides (Black & White, Color), 1986 and undated; 4 folders (Box 15)
  - Promotional event materials, 2010 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Materials for book signings, readings, and other events promoting the publication of Slow Burn.
  - Booksigning negatives, 1986 (Box 15)
  - Portrait of Jacobs at a book signing event, undated (Box 12)
  - Original (vintage) 59 prints and book graphics, 1986; 3 folders 8" x 10" (Box 3)
  - Archival Fiber silver gelatin exhibit prints, 1986; 7 folders 44 Prints in Box 10; 38 Prints in Box 11 11" x 14" (Box 10, Box 11)
  - Printer proof pages for limited edition, 2010 (Box 7)
  - Original (vintage) book prints with printer markings, 1985-1986; 3 folders 87 original book prints 8" x 10" (Box 4)
  - Original Xerox maquette for first edition, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Xerox maquette with revisions, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Original book work prints, 1986; 10 folders 443 prints 8" x 10" (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Work prints, 1986; 4 folders 38 prints 16" x 20" (Box 12)
  - Work prints, undated; 2 folders 2 inkjet prints and 19 silver gelatin prints 11" x 14" and assorted (Box 12)
  - Press clippings re: Centralia, Slow Burn, etc., 1986-1987 and undated; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Archival Fiber silver gelatin exhibit prints, 1986; 3 folders 16 prints 11 prints 16" x 20"; 3 prints 11" x 14"; 2 prints 8" x 10" (Box 12)
  - Exhibit captions, 1986 (Box 7)
  - Slow Burn reviews, press releases, and exhibit promotions, 1985-2010; 2 folders (Box 7, Box 15)
  - No Trespassing sign from Centralia Police Department, 1985 (Box 7)
  - Slow Burn working copy of published book, 1986 (Box 7)
  - Unbound printer proofs, 2010; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Proof pages, 2010 (Box 7, Oversize-folder 1)
  - Unbound printer proofs, Sonny Mekosh portrait, 2010 (Box 8)
  - Maquette revision with corrections, 2010 (Box 8)
  - Slow Burn published book, softcover, 2010 (Box 7)
  - Binders (2) of digital guide prints for 2010 reissue, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Slow Burn limited edition published book, 2010 (Box 7)
  - Mockup slipcover for 2010 reissue (Box 8)
  - Digital work prints, 2010; 109 items 109 prints 8.5" x 11" (Box 9)
  - Centralia oral history interviews, circa 1983-1986
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Please contact Research Services in advance of your visit to request the production of listening copies.
    - Jim Larkin / Jacki Chapman (Box 14, Audio-cassette Rl-11117-CS-0001)
    - Mary McGinley (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-0002)
    - Toni & Low Girolow (?) (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-0003)
    - A: Todd Dembowski. B: Flo Dembowski, 12/13/84 (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-0004)
    - Bishop ... (?) (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-0005)
    - A Side: Mary Tyson / Mary Gallagher. B Side: Mary Darrah (6/16) (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-0006)
    - A Side:Sheila Reemen / ... Kigert / Paige Mekesh. B Side: Mayor Wondo / Jerry Slavy (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-0007)
    - A: Toni & Low. B: Toni Grolanie (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-0008)
    - A: McGinley B: McGinley / Tory Maughan (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-0009)
    - N/A (no name) (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-00010)
    - Father McGinley (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-00011)
    - Colleen Russen (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-00012)
    - Eva + Joe Moran / Helen Womer (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-00013)
    - Side A: … / John Russen / Irish Caleyone (?) Irish. Side B: Caleyon (?) / Elizabeth Gillespie / Mayor John Wondo (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-00014)
    - Cruisers (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-00015)
    - Klink + Moran (Box 14, Audio-cassette RL-11117-CS-00016)
    - Release letters, permission to publish, etc., 1985-1986 (Box 4)
  - Inkjet exhibit prints, 2015; 3 folders 30 Prints 17" x 22" (Box 13)
    - P2 (cs. 190.17) (Box 13)
      [town landscape and houses with smoke in front]
    - P4 (cs. 76.23) (Box 13)
      [Centralia Mine Fire Is Our Future sign with girl]
    - P6 (cs 125.19) (Box 13)
      [Smoke coming out of pipe with a chain fence around it and houses in background]
    - P8 (cs 193.27) (Box 13)
      [Woman smiling and hugging boy]
    - P11 (cs 191.28) (Box 13)
      [Two men with hardhats talk with white smoke in the background]
    - P22 (cs 1.4) (Box 13)
      [Five boys in baseball uniforms sit on the steps in front of a house]
    - P27 (cs 26.18) (Box 13)
      [Man sits eating an apple in an office]
    - P31 (cs 133.25) (Box 13)
      [Silhouettes of signs in the night with a light behind and snow on the ground]
    - P34 (cs 146.19) (Box 13)
      [Man leaving room in background with Giangarlo Scientific Co. box in foreground]
    - P35 (cs 158.15) (Box 13)
      [Pipe with chain fence around it emitting smoke with the sky and clouds in the background]
    - P44 (cs 35.36) (Box 13)
      [Elderly woman looking at photograph of two women]
    - P47 (cs 15.5) (Box 13)
      [Smiling baby in stroller with fence and sign in background]
    - P52 (cs 134.28) (Box 13)
      [Night picture of empty road with signs and smoke in the background]
    - P53 (cs 146.5) (Box 13)
      [Man in background watches as someone tests the sink with a device in a house]
    - P55 (cs 106.14) (Box 13)
      [Woman in white sweater points at elderly woman in foreground in a building with people talking in the background]
    - P61 (cs 59.7) (Box 13)
      [Man sitting in armchair with various portraits on the wall, a doll house, and an empty armchair]
    - P63 (cs 98.31) (Box 13)
      [Chevrolet car with license plate "We Dig Coal"]
    - P67 (cs 149.13) (Box 13)
      [Man in mirror testing a bedroom with device]
    - P71 (cs 71.14) (Box 13)
      [Woman lying in bed and woman holding a notebook look at man who's holding something in his left hand]
    - P73 (cs 67.10) (Box 13)
      [Mother holding child in front of couch, as man with device stands in the right background]
    - P76 (cs 87.12) (Box 13)
      [Bride walks in white with flowers in her hand past a wall. A sign reads "Appalachian Regional Development Act of 1965"]
    - P103 (cs 49.13) (Box 13)
      [Woman stands with arm raised wearing shirt saying "The Hottest Town in Penna."]
    - P107 (cs 123.31) (Box 13)
      [Girl in dress and hat eats a lollipop with dolls on the floor around her]
    - P122 (cs 159.32) (Box 13)
      [Man in suit measures length of room with two boys lying on the couch]
    - P131 (cs 155.30) (Box 13)
      [Woman sits on rug with a cardboard box in front of her and an inflatable crocodile in a trashbag]
    - P132 (cs 153.36) (Box 13)
      [Woman sits on rug in dark room staring out the window, with a reflection of her in the background]
    - P135 (cs 156.4) (Box 13)
      [Two houses; a person is entering the white house, the black house has a "Notice No Trespassing" sign on it]
    - P139 (cs 156.4) (Box 13)
      [Elderly woman sits on couch looking into camera as a man moves items of of the house]
    - P145 (Box 13)
      [Bulldozer destroys house]
    - P147 (cs 168.36) (Box 13)
      [Two men stare down at the wreckage and debris of a home]
  - Correspondence with University of Pennsylvania Press re: Slow Burn publication, 1985-1986 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence re: Slow Burn publication, 1986-1995, 2008 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence with Heather Liston re: her father, William T. Liston's visit to Centralia, 2015 (Box 15)
    Includes color prints and negatives from Liston's visit, circa 1987.
  - T-shirt: Centralia: The Hottest Town in Penna, undated (Box 16)